(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So I arrived by truck with about 50 rebels
حسنا، وصلت بالشاحنة مع 50 من المتمردين
to the battle for Jalalabad
لمعركة جلال أباد
as a 19-year-old vegetarian surfer from Jacksonville, Florida.
كراكب أمواج نباتي في ال19 من عمره من جاكسونفيل، فلوريدا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I traded my Converse black low-tops
قايضت حذاء الكونفيرس الأسود ذي العلو المنخفض
for a pair of brown leather sandals
بزوج من الصنادل الجلدية البنية
and launched a rocket towards government tanks
وأطلقت صاروخا نحو دبابات الحكومة
that I couldn't even see.
التي لم أستطع رؤيتها حتى.
And this was my first time in Afghanistan.
وتلك كانت أول مرة أزور فيها أفغانستان.
Long before that I had grown up with the war,
وقبل ذلك بوقت طويل ترعرعت مع الحرب،
but alongside weekend sleepovers and Saturday soccer games
ولكن جنبا إلى جنب مع حفلات النوم الجماعي وألعاب كرة القدم في يوم السبت
and fistfights with racist children of the Confederacy
والصراع بالأيدي مع الأطفال العنصريين من الكونفدرالية
and religio-nationalist demonstrations
والمظاهرات الدينية-القومية
chanting, "Down with communism and long live Afghanistan,"
التي تردد، "تسقط الشيوعية وتعيش أفغانستان،"
and burning effigies of Brezhnev before I even knew what it meant.
وحرق دمى بريجنيف قبل أن أعرف ما تعنيه حتى.
But this is the geography of self.
ولكن هذه هي جغرافيا النفس.
And so I stand here today,
ولذا فإنني أقف هنا اليوم،
Afghan by blood, redneck by the grace of God,
أفغانيا بالدم وقرويا أمريكيا متعصبا بفضل الله،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
an atheist and a radically politicized artist
ملحد وفنان مسيس جذريا
who's been living, working and creating in Afghanistan
والذي يعيش ويشتغل ويصنع في أفغانستان
for the last nine years.
طوال السنوات التسع الماضية.
Now there are a lot of wonderful things that you could
والآن هناك الكثير من الأمور الرائعة التي يمكن
make art about in Afghanistan,
جعل الفن يتمحور حولها في أفغانستان،
but personally I don't want to paint rainbows;
ولكن شخصيا لا أريد رسم قوس قزح؛
I want to make art that disturbs identity
أريد إنتاج فن يزعج الهوية
and challenges authority
ويتحدى السلطة
and exposes hypocrisy
ويفضح النفاق
and reinterprets reality
ويعيد تفسير الواقع
and even uses kind of an imaginative ethnography
بل ويستخدم نوعا من اﻻثنوغرافيا الخيالية
to try and understand the world that we live in.
لمحاولة فهم العالم الذي نعيش فيه.
I want to spend a day in the life of a jihadi gangster
أريد قضاء يوم واحد في حياة رجل عصابة من المجاهدين
who wears his jihad against the communists
والذي يرتدي أدوات جهاده ضد الشيوعيين
like popstar bling
مثل مجوهرات نجوم البوب
and uses armed religious intimidation and political corruption
ويستخدم التخويف الديني المسلح والفساد السياسي
to make himself rich.
لجعل نفسه غنيا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And where else can the jihadi gangster go, but run for parliament
وماذا قد يفعل رجل العصابات الجهادي سوى أن يترشح للبرلمان
and do a public installation campaign
والقيام بحملة تثبيت عامة
with the slogan: "Vote for me! I've done jihad, and I'm rich."
تحت شعار: "صوتوا لي! لقد قمت بالجهاد، وأنا غني. "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And try and use this campaign to expose these mafiosos
ومحاولة استخدام هذه الحملة لفضح رجال المافيا
who are masquerading as national heroes.
الذين يتظاهرون بأنهم أبطال وطنيون.
I want to look into corruption in Afghanistan
أريد أن أفحص الفساد في أفغانستان
through a work called "Payback"
من خلال عمل يسمى "الاسترداد"
and impersonate a police officer,
وانتحال شخصية ضابط شرطة،
set up a fake checkpoint on the street of Kabul and stop cars,
وإقامة نقطة تفتيش وهمية على شارع كابول، وإيقاف السيارات،
but instead of asking them for a bribe, offering them money
ولكن بدلاً من أن أطلب منهم رشوة، أقدم لهم المال
and apologizing on behalf of the Kabul Police Department --
وأعتذر باسم إدارة شرطة كابول-
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
and hoping that they'll accept this 100 Afghanis on our behalf.
وعلى أمل أنها سوف تقبل هذا 100 من الأفغاني بالنيابة عنا.
I want to look at how, in my opinion,
أنا أريد أن أنظر إلى كيف، في رأيي،
the conflict in Afghanistan has become conflict chic.
صار الصراع في أفغانستان صراعا أنيقا.
The war and the expatriate life that comes with it
الحرب وحياة المغتربين التي تأتي معها
have created this environment of style and fashion
خلقت هذه البيئة من الأناقة والأزياء
that can only be described
التي لا يمكن وصفها
through creating a fashion line for soldiers and suicide bombers
إلا من خلال إنشاء خط أزياء للجنود ومنفذي العمليات الانتحارية
where I take local Afghan fox fur and add it to a flack jacket
حيث تأخذ فراء ثعلب أفغاني محلي وتضيفه إلى سترة واقية من الرصاص
or make multiple interior pockets
أو إدراج جيوب داخلية متعددة
on fashionable neo-traditional vests.
على السترات التقليدية العصرية.
And I'd like to look at how taking a simple Kabul wheelbarrow
وأود أن أنظر في كيفية أخذ عربة كابول يدوية بسيطة
and putting it on the wall amidst Kipling's call of 1899
ووضعها على الجدار وسط نداء كيبلينغ لسنة 1899
to generate dialogue about how I see contemporary development initiatives
لبدء حوار حول الكيفية التي أرى بها مبادرات التنمية المعاصرة
being rooted in yesterday's colonial rhetoric
وهي متجذرة في الخطاب الاستعماري للأمس
about a "white man's burden"
حول "عبء الرجل الأبيض"
to save the brown man from himself
لإنقاذ الرجل الأسمر من نفسه
and maybe even civilize him a bit.
وربما حتى تهذيبه قليلاً.
But doing these things, they can get you in jail,
ولكن القيام بهذه الأشياء، قد يرميك في السجن،
they can be misunderstood, misinterpreted.
يمكن أن يساء فهمها، أو يساء تفسيرها.
But I do them because I have to,
ولكنني أقوم بذلك لأنه أمر لازم،
because the geography of self mandates it.
لأن جغرافية النفس توصي بذلك.
That is my burden. What's yours?
هذا هو عبئي. ما هو عبئكم؟
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)